父亲 我的父亲 你在船上吗
Vater. Mein Vater, bist du an Bord?
爸爸，您在这里吗
Vater, bist du hier?
爸爸
Vater.
爸爸！
Vater!
该死……真他妈的该死！
Bloody hell... Bloody, bloody hell!
医生说 没有尸体他不来
The doctor says he won't come until he has a body, sir.
什么 什么 他认为底下就只眼球而已？
What? What, he thinks it's just an eyeball down there?
有人靠着码头掉下去了？
Somebody leaned over the quay and it dropped out?
他说死要见尸 头儿
He says he needs a body, sir.
不可理喻
Unbelievable.
这儿有点东西 就在这儿 警长 警长！是 好的
I've got something here. Right here, Sarge. Sarge! Right, good.
跟他说我们有了
Tell him we've got one.
要通知詹特利总督察吗
Shouldn't we call out Chief Inspector Gently?
不必 他休息 好了
No, no. He's on leave. Right.
继续 医生
Go on, Doctor.
请让一让 往后站站
Please let me through. Stand back.
但我得和一把手谈谈
But then I need to talk to whoever is in charge.
呃 谁是管事的 没事了 我就是 有何贵干
Well, who is in charge? It's all right, I'm in charge. How can I help?
昨晚起我就没见着我父亲 好了
I am missing my father since last night. OK, right.
我们在这儿碰面 一起上船 我就听说水里有具尸体
Since we are to come here, to meet and go on our boat and I am hearing now there is a body in the water!
呃 是 请问尊姓大名 先生
Er, yeah. Can I take your name please, sir?
威尔海姆・史迈克……我父亲叫冈特・史迈克
Wilhelm Schmeikel...and my father is Gunter Schmeikel.
冈特・史迈克
Gunter Schmeikel.
我是警探长约翰・巴克斯
I'm Detective Sergeant John Bacchus.
-那边的船是你的吗 先生？-求你了
Now, is that your boat over there, sir? Please.
我没必要跟你说 我要和长官谈
I have no need to talk to you... I wish to speak to the commanding officer.
-我是负责人 史迈克先生 -你？-是 -不 区区一个警长？
I am in charge, Mr Schmeikel. You? Yeah. No. A mere sergeant?
警探长 实际上
Detective sergeant, actually.
不不不……你不明白
No, no no...you do not understand.
-我父亲失踪了 他是重要人物 非常重要 -是 我们尽力
My father is missing. He's an important man, very important. Yeah. We'll try our best.
不不 还不够好 无法接受…… 威尔海姆！那是冈特
No, no. That's not good enough. It's unacceptable... Wilhelm! Das ist Gunter.
先生 先生 先生 求你了 我要…… 抱歉 亲爱的
Sir. Sir, sir. Please, I need to... Excuse me, sorry, pet.
你能告诉我那个被找到的男人……
Can you just tell me the man that's been recovered...
是我的岳父…… 威尔海姆的父亲
Is my father-in-law... It's Wilhelm's father...
冈特・史迈克！冈特・史迈克
Gunter Schmeikel! Gunter Schmeikel.
为什么不叫我
Why didn't you call me?
因为三十分钟前它只是个不明眼球
Because 30 seconds ago it was just an unidentified eyeball.
我以为你休息呢
I thought you were on leave?
现在不了 不了 好吧 好吧
Not now, I'm not. Right. Right.
那么 有我的事了吗
Is there anything I can do, then?
敢情来杯茶？
Get you a cup of tea, perhaps?
不 谢了 看尸体
No, thanks. Look at the body.
呃 眼球被渔民钩出来了
Well, the eyeball was hooked out by a fisherman.
不是说眼球 重点错 警长
Not talking about the eyeball, Sergeant.
他扭曲得没人形了 是 会到那步的 看他的手 看到什么没
He's all twisted. Yeah, we'll get to that. Look at his hands. What do you see?
没 表明什么
Nothing. What's that tell you?
他没做挣扎
He didn't struggle.
是 因为如果试图逃生的话他会把手撕碎的 但他没有
Yeah, because he would have torn his hands to shreds trying to get out of here, but he didn't.
把他翻个身
Turn him over.
把夹克和衬衫拉上来
Pull up his jacket and shirt.
脊椎断了
That spine's been snapped.
没挣扎是因为他在这一重击下瘫痪了
He didn't struggle because the attack paralysed him.
-意思是他在入水前还是活着的 -正确
Meaning he was alive when he entered the water. Correct.
叫医生别来了吗
？Shall I call off the doctor, then?
我来推定死亡时间 赌一把？
I'll have a stab at the time of death, if you like. You fancy a bet?
十或十二个小时
Ten or twelve hours.
好吧 算上我了
All right, you're on.
-所以你就是路过 是吧？-呃 你知道的
So you were just passing then, were you? Well, you know.
我在车站扫了一眼 是的
I had a look in at the station, yeah.
那周你休假？
On your week off?
我们有人了吗
We got a name yet?
是的 冈特・史迈克
Yeah. Gunter Schmeikel.
那是什么 德国人 澳洲佬 还是瑞士的
What's that, German, Austrian, Swiss?
呃 反正不是东北人 是不
Well, it's not Geordie, is it?
泰勒正在跟他的儿子儿媳说话
Taylor's talking to his son and his daughter-in-law...
他们估计那儿的船是他的
They reckon that's his boat over there.
干得漂亮
Very nice.
钱包呢还是现金？
Any wallet or cash?
没 只有这个
No. Just this.
肯定花了不少钱 这个
Must've cost a few bob, this.
有些还好
All right for some.
我想他们战败了
I thought they lost the war.
值班簿
Log book.
上面说他六天前离开汉堡了
It says here they left Hamburg six days ago.
我德语O级
I did German 'O' level.
全班领先
Top of me class.
哟 那我可松了口气
Well, that's a relief.
冈特・史迈克名下的护照
Passport in the name of Gunter Schmeikel.
是他 好的
It's him, all right.
旅行袋 看看有没有钱包
Overnight bag. See if there's a wallet.
没没 没有
No. No, there isn't.
嘿 呃 听着 我17岁时有个德国笔友 从杜塞尔多夫过来了
Hey, eh, listen, I had this German pen pal that came over to stay from Dusseldorf when I was 17.
艾柯 她的名字
Elke, she was called.
啊 她……头发到这儿
Ah, man, she was... Hair down to here.
天使脸蛋
Face like an angel.
上帝 她真，真是美啊
God, she was, she was beautiful.
好
Good.
我带他的儿子儿媳和回旅馆 先生
I took the son and daughter-in-law back to their hotel, sir...
在山上一里左右 你让他俩落单了？
About a mile up the hill. You left them on their own?
你从未说过他们是嫌疑人啊 好吧他们当然是
You never said they were suspects. Well, of course they're suspects, man.
那帮家伙当中有人说死者
Some folks in the crowd said that the deceased was drinking
昨晚和一些当地人在海员休息室喝酒 好样的 泰勒
with some locals in the Mariner's Rest last night. Well done, Taylor.
我们用你的车
We'll use your car.
呃 你怎么把婴儿车塞进名爵的
Well, how do you fit a pram into an MG?
塞不下就不要硬撑
Three into two does not go.
我数学什么的都过了
I did 'O' Level Maths an' all.
史迈克夫人在咖啡厅 还有……
Mrs Schmeikel's in the coffee lounge, and...
是的 史迈克先生还在自己的房间里……打电话
Yes. Mr Schmeikel's still in his room...on the phone.
-房号？-14
Room number? 14.
你不介意我听吧 头儿？
D'you mind if I listen in, Guv?
抱歉 我没听清 给我耳麦好吗 有劳了 亲爱的
I'm sorry, I didn't quite catch that. Can I have the headphones, please, pet?
谢了
Thanks.
行
Yep.
什么
What?
他在说德语 他和另一个男人
He's speaking in German. Him and another man.
说什么
Saying what?
这个嘛有点难度 在你看不到唇部动作的时候
Well, it's a bit tricky, isn't it, when you can't see the lips moving?
或者是因为说话的人没长一张天使脸蛋？
Or if the speaker doesn't have the face of an angel?
麻烦打断他
Interrupt him, please.
告诉他詹特利总督察想和他谈谈 就现在
Tell him Detective Inspector Gently would like to speak to him. Right now.
去叫他
Go and get him.
史迈克先生？
Mr Schmeikel?
是的 有位詹特利探长找
Yes, I have a Detective Gently for yer.
总探长 这才像话
Chief Inspector. This is more like it.
无意冒犯 警长
No offence intended, Sergeant.
好了 詹特利总探长
Right. Chief Inspector Gently.
是……谢谢
Yes... Thank you.
现在你可以走了
You can leave now.
我们……？
Shall we...?
我父亲整晚都在和他所谓的……
My father had been drinking all evening with his so-called...
朋友们喝酒……然后我就想他是不是想到小船里去……还有
friends...and, I'm imagining him trying to get into the dinghy...and, well,
他进去了 如果我告诉你们我们觉得他的背断了呢
in he goes. What if I told you we think his back was broken?
亲爱的上帝啊
Lieber Gott.
-你没事吧 史迈克夫人？-没事
Are you all right, Mrs Schmeikel? Yes.
现在 你提到过你父亲来头不小
Now, you mentioned that your father was important.
他在不来梅市有一家大型制药公司
He owns a large pharmaceutical company in Bremen.
那就让他变得重要了？
That makes him important, does it?
能告诉我你的手是怎么回事吗 史迈克先生？
Can you tell me what happened to your hands, Mr Schmeikel?
这个 这是在北海不擅航行付出的代价
This. This you get from the North Sea when you're no good at sailing!
荒谬！整个一出闹剧！
Ridiculous! This whole thing is ridiculous.
哪里荒谬了 先生？
Ridiculous in what way, sir?
我父亲 他 呃 是一名战犯 在44年空战中被击落……
My father, he, er, was a prisoner of war...shot down in '44...
德国空军……轰炸机飞行员……
Luftwaffe...a bomber pilot...
然后就获编了？
and, then... billeted?
获编了 对
Billeted, yeah.
在一家农场里获编排住下了……显然 20年后我必须去拜访投宿 以便能“学会”
Billeted, yes, on a pig farm...which 20 years later I apparently must visit and stay at so I can "learn"
如何经营养猪场
how pig farmers do business...
所以我父亲 他待在农场……然后
So my father, he stays on the farm...and
-我们来这儿 你和你父亲就这事争执过吗
-we come here. Did you argue with your father over this?
他们无时不吵 这……
They argue all the time, it's...
这些养猪场农民 就是昨晚和他在酒吧的那些朋友吗
These pig farmers, are they the friends he was in the pub with last night?
哈德门一家 是！哈德门一家
The Hardyments, yeah! The Hardyments.
冈特 冈特 过来 咱们唱首虫歌 唱虫歌
Gunter, Gunter. C'mon, let's do the worm song. Do the worm song.
不不不 我记不得了
No, no, no, I can't remember it!
你当然记得！谁教你的 嗯？走开 老兄 让我们时光倒流二十年！
Course yer can! Who taught yer, eh? Away, man, let's wind the clock back 20 year!
别出声 伙计们 吸口气 让我告诉你一件可怕的事
?Whisht lads, hold yer gobs I'll tell yer all an awful story,
别出声 伙计们 吸口气 让我告诉你踢走虫子的事
?Whisht lads, hold yer gobs An' I'll tell yer 'boot the worm! ?
而你身在何处
And where were you?
我们在这里……我们在这里一直到十点一刻和我父亲在码头见面
We were here... We were here until we were to meet my father at the quayside at 10.15...
他坚持让我们睡在船里以便捕捉早潮
He insisted we sleep on the boat to catch an early tide.
所以 你昨晚离开旅馆了 什么时候？
So, you left the hotel last night, what time?
十点钟 对吗？十点……是
Ten o'clock, yes? Ten...ja.
你看见或会见什么人了吗
Did you see or meet anyone?
没 没人
No. No-one...
当我父亲半小时后还没出现 我们就回这里了
And when my father doesn't come after half an hour, we come back here.
你父亲有个钱包吗
Did your father have a wallet?
是的 在他夹克的内侧口袋里
Yes. The inside pocket of his jacket.
为什么 不见了吗
Why, it is gone?
是的 请问
Yes. Could I ask
你早前是跟谁在
who were you talking to earlier,
打电话？
on the phone?
我得通知公司……让他们知情
I had to inform the company... to let them know.
我岳父的员工就像一家人
My father-in-law's employees are like his family. Halt du dich da raus.
-要给你们护照吧……我这就去拿 -是的
You will be needing our passports... I will go get them for you. Yes.
用德语小声交谈
THEY WHISPER IN GERMAN
不好意思
Excuse me,
说英语行吗
could you speak in English, please?
抱歉 她英文不太好
Excuse me, her English is not good enough.
嗯……我必须……不择手段
Um... I must... By all means.
我懂德语 我只是口语不行
I can read German... I just, I can't do the oral.
可怜的老艾柯 好了
Poor old Elke. Right.
你一旦收集到史迈克的护照就找人追踪查尔纳的下落
Once you've collected the Schmeikels' passports, get someone to track down China...
不管醉醒 我要见他的人 尽快
I want him here drunk or sober, as soon as you can.
为什么非得他啊
Why do we need him?
只管照做
Just do it, please.
他们在杜伦的大小酒馆找查尔纳了
They're looking in all the pubs in Durham for China.
还有病理学家已经开膛破肚了 所以……
And the pathologist's ripping the body open already, so...
好了 我们到猪农那里走一趟
Right. Let's visit a pig farmer.
哦 好的
Oh, right.
一分钟
One minute.
他们土豪的很 有些猪农
They're pretty well off, some of these pig farmers.
这车一百块？ 是
A hundred quid for this car? Yeah.
一辆名爵一百磅 性价比高啊！-哦 可不
A hundred pound for an MG is a bargain, man! Oh, yeah,
那你为什么贱卖
so why are you selling it so cheap?
你知道的
You know.
不宽裕吗 警长
Have you got money problems, Sergeant?
没
No.
是 什么？是手头稍紧还是负债累累
Yes. What, are you just feeling the pinch, or are you actually in debt?
-你欠多少 -头儿 这没什么 我应付不了……
How much do you owe? Look, sir, it's nothing I can't manage...
-我很快就要参加探长考试了 我会过的…… -嗯 是的我肯定你能行
I'm taking my Inspector's exams soon...which I'll pass... Well, yes, I'm sure you'll pass.
但最近又没职位空缺
But I can't see a vacancy for an Inspector coming up in the near future.
呃 等有了我就会调到另一个部门去了
Well, then I'll transfer to another force where they've got more room.
更大的地方 那得多久
Somewhere bigger. And how long's that going to take?
看吧 头儿 一切尽在掌握
Look, Sir, it's all in hand.
是 不错……因为对负债的警察而言 遍地是诱惑
Yeah, good...because a copper in debt is open to temptation.
实际上 我反感那么做 什么？你觉得不会发生在你身上？
I resent that, actually. What? You think it can't happen to you?
屡见不鲜 多少锦绣前程就此断送
I've seen it a dozen times. A dozen promising careers ruined.
友情建议 仅此而已
Just trying to offer some friendly advice.
是 头儿 收到 “切勿负债”
Yes, sir, I heard your advice. "Don't get into debt".
谢您的小贴士 我都在卖车了 不是？
Thanks for the tip. I'm selling me car, aren't I?
抱歉抱歉
Sorry. Sorry.
老实讲 船到桥头自然直
Honestly, it'll all get straightened out.
我觉得史迈克夫人欲言又止
I reckon Mrs Schmeikel knows more than she's allowed to say.
哦 什么味道
Oh, what's that smell?!
鞋子……
Shoes...
你们谁啊 想干啥 警探巴克斯
Who are yous, like, and what d'yer want? Detective Sergeant Bacchus...
怎么了 爹？那个屁精是谁？公子哥似的
How, Da! Who's that flash bugger? Looks like a toff.
下午
Afternoon.
我是詹特利总督察 这是巴克斯警探
I'm Detective Chief Inspector Gently. This is Detective Sergeant Bacchus.
我们想问你一些问题 麻烦了
We'd like to ask you a few questions, please.
一个伦敦佬！还是大人物
A bloody Londoner! And a big-wig an' all.
不能更糟了！欢迎来到南北分界 先生
Gets worse and worse! Welcome to the North/South divide, sir.
好吧 我正要去用餐……所以不想在那干等的话就进来
Well, I'm just about to have me dinner...so either wait there, or away in.
我震惊了……
I'm shocked...shocked,
我很震惊
I am, I'm shocked.
是的 我们昨晚和他一起
I am. We were with him last night!
谁会干掉冈特？！
Who'd wanna do Gunter?!
没人……为什么他们要这样？！
Naybody...why would they?!
我们开走的时候跟他招手了
I gave him a wave as we drove off!
我吃不下去了
I can barely eat!
我能问你昨晚的事吗
Can I ask you about last night?
嗯 随便你问
Aye, ask what yer like, aye!
你去了船员休息室
You went to the Mariners.
是 怎么了
Aye! And what happened?
因为自从冈特被编宿以来我就没见过他了
Cos I haven't seen Gunter since he was billeted here...
但只要他一回来 就会到他的小阁楼里 仍然像个战犯
But as soon as he's back, he's back in his loft where he was as a PoW...
他在那儿睡了两晚 猪场里的各种事情他也帮忙
Two nights he slept there. He helps out with the pigs an' everything...
现在他是个截然不同的农民了
Him an altogether different type of farmer now...
一名制药商 是啊 一名制药商 对
A pharmaceutical man. Aye, a pharmaceutical man, that's right, aye.
但他做事就像二十年前那样 你知道 他乐在其中
But he mucks in like it's 20 years ago, you know, and he loves it.
我们带他去哈德良城墙……因为我教他怎么成为鸟人
We took him to Hadrian's Wall...cos I taught him to be a bird man,
很少有鸟飞来 你知道 有很多事要干
and there's rare ones flying in, you know, quite a to-do about it,
你们知道这是他的最后一晚 我们都在馆子里
and 'fore yer know it's his last night and we're all in the pub.
所有酒水都是他请
He's buying drinks for everybody.
不 真的 你已经请得够多了
No, really, already you have given enough!
那我明天走的时候
Then, when I'm gone, tomorrow,
全场还是算我的！一杯淡黑 先生 谢谢！
the drinks are still on me! One Black and Tan, sir. Thank you!
不用找了
Keep it, please.
唱虫歌！
Singing the Worm song!
是 是
Aye. Aye...
他现在要告诉你们虫的一切
He'll tell yer all about the worm now.
别出声 伙计们 为了请你们喝酒的男人保持呼吸 冈特・史迈克！
Whisht lads and hold yer gobs for the man who's buyin' drinks, Gunter Schmeikel!
必胜……必胜！
Sieg heil... Sieg heil!
哦诶！不要记恨 你们！
Oy! Forgive and forget, you lot!
否则我扇你巴掌！
Or I'll slap yer chops for yer!
麦布斯
Mabs...
麦布斯 这全是开玩笑的！
Mabs, it's all in jest!
他钓到一条鱼 他觉得很稀奇
?He catched a fish upon his heuk He thought leukt varry queer
是哪一种鱼儿 年轻的兰普顿不知道
?But what'n a kind of fish it was Young Lambton couldn't tell
他不急着带它回家 就把它放在井下
?He wasn't fash to carry it home So he hoyed it doon a well
别出声 伙计们 吸口气 让我告诉你一件可怕的事
?Whisht lads, hold yer gobs I'll tell yer all an awful story
别出声 伙计们 吸口气 让我告诉你踢走虫子的事
?Whisht lads, hold yer gobs, I'll tell yer boot the worm! ?
是 非常好 谢谢
Yeah, be very nice. Thank you.
他就像冈特的家人 是吧
He's like Gunter's family, isn't he?
什么 他说你是冈特一伙的
What was that? He says you're a lot like Gunter.
不是轰炸机飞行员了吧你？哦 不 不是轰炸机飞行员了 不
Weren't a bomber pilot, though, were yer? Oh, no. Not a bomber pilot, no.
不 你要像个轰炸机飞行员样 上点档次！
No, you gotta be posh to be a bomber pilot!
不是那套保守党派的上档次……
Not yer Alec Douglas-Home posh...
但是比你强
But posher than you.
是啊 他会喜欢你的
Aye, he'd have liked you.
你也会喜欢他 好吧 人人都爱老冈特
You'd have liked him, well, everybody liked Gunter.
晚上结束的时候发生什么了？- 他要回德国
End of the evening, what happened? Well, he's back to Deutschland
早潮的时候 所以我们从馆子出来 拥抱他
first tide, so we come out the pub and give him a hug.
那是几点？
What time was that?
十点整……我们起得早 你知道的
Ten o'clock sharp... We're up early in the morning, you know.
从哪条路回家的
Which way did you go home?
-沿着码头返回山上的 -看见其他人了吗
Along the quayside and back up the hill. See anybody else?
我想没有 不对 有 我们看到了！
Don't think so, no. Yeah, we did!
他的儿子 在旅馆附近
That son of his, near his hotel.
因为我说了句“你跟他走岔了”
Cos I said, "Oh, you've missed him!"
我很抱歉 但他不待见咱们
I'm sorry, but he didn't like us.
啊 你也不喜欢他……我们注意到了！
Ah, you didn't like him... We noticed!
谁会喜欢那个自大狂？
Well, what's to like about that arrogant shite?
所以你看见他和妻子沿着码头走
So you saw him and his wife walking towards the quayside.
不不 她不在 就他一个人
No, no, she wasn't with him. He was on his own...
难道她不会…… 她胆小
Wouldn't have her down...she's just a mouse.
有什么需要的 尽管叫我
Anything I can do, just give us a shout!
谢谢
Thank you.
-你看到那个在周围晃悠的年轻小伙子了吗 左边那个 -看到了
Did you see the young lad skulking around? The one that left. I did...
说曹操曹操到
Speak of the devil.
昨晚在酒馆
In the pub last night.
酒吧后面有个新来的小伙子叫夏弗斯
There was this new bloke behind the bar called Shavers...
一个大混蛋 你不会去招惹他的
A big bastard, like, yer wouldn't cross him.
不管怎样 我们和冈特在一起
Anyway, we're with Gunter.
在酒吧的我一哥们说夏弗斯语不惊人死不休纳粹那些事
A mate of mine at the bar says Shavers has been mouthing off
在冈特的啤酒里小便 还放言道要做得更甚 知道吗
about the Nazis an' that, an' how he pissed in Gunter's beer and said he had a mind to do more, you know?
当一些人走出来抗议 他的走狗就跟着他
And when a few others walked out in protest, he gans with 'em.
-别出声 伙计们 吸口气 让我告诉你一件可怕的事 -这是几点的事
?Whisht lads, hold yer gobs I'll tell yer all an awful story... ?
What time was this?
刚过九点？
Just after nine?
好吧 谢了…… 保持联系
Right, thanks... We'll be in touch.
在我们要走的时候我又看见他了
I saw him again that night when we were leaving.
在停车场
In the car park,
背阴的地方 观察咱们……我感觉不妙 就像 但……
in the shadows, watching us... I didn't have a good feeling, like, but...
和冈特道别后再回头看 他就不见了
say goodbye to Gunter and look back, and he'd gone.
是夏弗斯？
This is Shavers?
是啊
Aye.
奇克・夏弗斯 你看见他往哪走了吗
Chick Shavers. Did you see where he went?
没 我们只是开走了
Nah, we just drove off.
之后看见什么人没？
And did you see anyone after that?
只有鞋子上的狗屎
Only Dog Shite On Yer Shoe.
你知道 冈特的儿子 从山上下来
Y'know, Gunter's son. Coming down the hill.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢了
Thanks.
嘿！
Hoy!
你知道开车的小诀窍吗
Y'know that owld knack ya drivin'?
25镑买废品？
Will you take 25 pound for scrap?
不 我不愿意
No. I won't.
你再碰我试试！进来
Touch me one more time! Get in.
夏弗斯先生 感谢您前来 请坐
Mr Shavers, thanks for coming in. Please sit down.
不 谢了 我不会停下来的
No, ta, I won't be stopping.
有人举报声称你曾在一位特别顾客的啤酒里排便
e've had reports that you claimed to have urinated in the beer of a particular customer last night...
在克劳特 是啊 我干了三次呢 一个帝国一次！
In the Kraut's, aye. I did it three times, one for each Reich!
你清楚史迈克先生今早被发现死亡了吧
You're aware Mr Schmeikel was found dead this morning.
呃 如果死因是尿液中毒 你们抓到人了
Well, if it's from urine poisoning, I'm yer man.
他死没死你毫不关心？看
You don't mind that he's dead? Look.
我不知道战争期间你做了什么 坐下 向民众大放厥词 释放隔阂的烟幕……
I don't know what you were doing in the war. Sit down. Yelling at folk to put up black-out curtains...
我是把那些渣滓从哪来的踢回哪去 还有我亲眼所见 有事长埋于此 于此！
I was kicking that scum back where they came from, and I saw things that are buried into here! Here!
你和你们世界的其他人可以原谅忘记 但不包括我
You and the rest of the world can forgive and forget... But not me.
淡定 我们手上有你了
Calm down. I've had it with you!!
我不介意
I'm all right.
我想念我的使命了
I missed my vocation.
怀疑脊柱断了
Suspected broken back.
其它和我们估计的一样
Everything else just as we thought.
-泰勒 -在
-Taylor. -Sir.
他们告诉我你喜欢摔跤
They tell me you're a wrestling fan.
哦，我妈喜欢，我只是为了带她去罢了
Oh, well, me mam is sir, I just take her along, like.
切克・谢弗斯听说过吗？
Name Chick Shavers mean anything to you?
对，我在波维克见过他一次…
Oh, aye, I saw him in Berwick once...
他现在退休了，膝盖不行了。他是块难啃的骨头
He's retired now, did his knee in. Oh, he was a nasty piece of work.
不过干得非常不赖
Played the part well, though.
把波罗洲那个野人打得很惨
Did some horrible things to The Wild Man of Borneo.
有一次几乎把他的背打断了
Nearly broke his back once.
-谢谢你 -是
-Thank you. -Sir.
如果我们把他拷起来，你觉得你能自己对付谢弗斯吗？
So if we cuff him, d'you reckon you can manage Shavers on your own?
-当然能 -好的
Yeah, of course. Good.
不过我应该…
Well, I should, um...
站在他够不着的地方
stay out of his reach though.
我反对纳粹来这里到处挥舞他们的钞票！
I object to Nazis coming here and flashing their money around.
我反对。因为――我的钱在哪里？嗯？
I object, OK? Cos where's my money, eh?
我的呢？我以为我们是战胜国！
Where's mine? I thought we won the war!
现在是1964年了，谢弗斯先生
This is 1964, Mr Shavers.
你倒是腰包鼓鼓的！
There speaks a man whose pockets are full!
听着
Listen...
我不主动去找他们，可如果他们在我门口出现，还在我面前挥舞钞票，
I don't go looking for them, right? But if they turn up on my doorstep and wave it in my face then yeah,
我就会在他们的啤酒里撒尿，老乡们会鼓励地拍咱的背！
I'll put piss in their beer, and folk'll pat us on the back for doing it!
-你还干了什么了？ -你什么意思，还？
-What else did you do? -What d'you mean, what else?
我们有目击证人说在冈特・施麦克离开酒馆时你在停车场
We have a witness that places you in the car park when Gunter Schmeikel left the pub.
证人？你不是说那个弱智吧？
Witness. Don't yer mean half-wit?
哈迪曼家的？
One of the Hardyments?
说他弱智还差不多！
Witless, more like!
-谢弗斯先生，你有没有跟踪施麦克回到码头？ -没
-Mr Shavers, did you follow Gunter Schmeikel down to the quay? -No.
因为他的背被打断了
Because his back was broken, see.
你很有本事做到这个，不是吗？
You're quite capable of doing that, aren't you?
不，不，不 你不能！
No. No, no, no, no. No, you don't!
哇哦！
Whoa!
听着…
Look...
冷静一下
Just calm down, all right.
我们接着来
Just get on with it.
好了
All right.
我的确去了码头，没错
I did go to the quayside, aye.
不过是正要回来，这是实话
But I was on me way back, and this is the truth, right?
因为我承认我恨他们
Cos I admit it. I hate 'em.
我恨德国鬼子，不错，我确实想干点什么，我知道能干什么
I hate Jerries, and all right, I did want to do somet hing else and I knew what that something was, so I
所以我去了码头，准备松开他们的小船
went down to the quay to set their boat adrift.
这时大概9点
This is about nine.
我到他们那条豪华小船的时候周围没有人
And I arrive, and there's their flash boat with no-one around, or, I think
或者我觉得没有人，然后我发现了一辆轿车，里面的人打开了灯，所以我转过了身
there's no-one around, but then I clock this car, cos whoever's in it turns on some light so I turn away.
等等，等等
Hang about, hang about.
-那是谁？ -我不知道
-Who was it? -I don't know.
那你……你没认出他们？
Well, didn't...didn't you recognise them?
我又没在看！我是在等着把他们的船松开
I'm not looking, am I? I'm waiting to set the boat adrift.
我只希望那个家伙走人，可他没走，就坐在那里！
I just want the bloke to go, but he stays, he just sits there!
冷静
Calm down.
等了半小时以后，我没兴趣了，放弃了回到酒馆
And after half an hour of waiting, I lose me appetite, give up, go back to the pub and
我到那里时哈迪曼家和德国佬正在往家走。这都是大实话
arrive just as the Hardyments and the Kraut are heading off home. And that's the God's honest.
-那车是什么样的？ -我不知道！
-And what type of car was it? -I don't know!
一辆深色的沙龙
A da rk saloon.
我不能肯定，我只能告诉你这么多
I can't be sure. That's all I can tell you.
好的
Right.
我说切克・谢弗斯不是你的真名，对不对？
Would I be right in thinking that "Chick Shavers" isn't your real name?
这是我的艺名，现在大家都叫我这个名字
Well, it's the name I used professionally. And i t's the one I'm known as now.
好吧
Right, yeah, see,
恐怕我们需要你出生证上的名字
I'm afraid we need your name that's on your birth certificate.
-马尔科姆・费雷 -什么？
-Malcolm Fairey. -Sorry?
马尔科姆・费雷
Malcolm Fairey!
-谢谢 -娘娘腔
-Thank you. -Poofter.
你知道，没有一个当地人…
You know, none of the locals...
当然，除了蓝色角落里的那个“仙女”
Well, except for the Fairey in the blue corn er...
没有任何人说过我们这位德国轰炸机飞行员的坏话
none of them have a bad word to say about our Germ an bomber.
是啊，冈特・施麦克似乎是个挺正派的人
Yeah, Gunter Schmeikel seems to have been a decent fellow.
是啊，是啊，作为一个往人头上扔炸弹的人来说
Oh, yeah, yeah. For somebody who dropped bombs on people.
你知道 我还记得那些被轰炸的码头
You know, I can just about remember the docks being bombed.
平民被炸死
Civilians were killed.
无辜的群众
Innocent people.
听说过德累斯顿吗
Ever hear of Dresden?
我们的轰炸机在那里制造的火风暴杀了5万百姓
Our bombs created a fire storm that killed 50,000 civilians.
据我所知没什么特别的原因
For no particular reason that I can think of,
只为了恐吓一个民族
except to terrorise a nation.
德国人在发动该死的战争之前就该想到这一点
Yeah, well, the Germans should've thought of that before they started the bloody war.
对
Right.
切克・谢弗斯告诉我们在他离开时码头有辆车
Chick Shavers tells us that there was a car at the quayside when he left.
-对 -等他回到酒馆时，哈迪曼一家正在对冈特说再见，
-Yep. -When he got to the pub, the Hardyments were saying goodbye to Gunter,
然后哈迪曼家开车走了，在山上他们看到威尔海姆下来
and the Hardyments drive along the road, up the hill where they see Wilhelm coming down.
对，他是一个人，没带他的妻子
Yeah, and he's on his own. He hasn't got his wife with him.
-根据哈迪曼家的说法 -对
According to the Hardyments. Yeah.
同时，冈特从酒馆走去了码头
Meanwhile, Gunter's walking from the pub to the quay.
我们推测，他就是在那里遇到了杀他的人
We assume, where he met his maker.
我们去看看施麦克他们什么时候回酒店的
Let's see what time the Schmeikels booked back into their hotel.
-好 -应该很有意思
-OK. -Should be interesting.
-查尔纳？ -你说了“不管醉的还是醒的”，头儿
-China? -Well, you did say "drunk or sober", Guv.
不，不，巴克斯先生。我清醒得像只羊，准备并愿意
No, no, Mr Bacchus. I'm sober as a lamb, and ready and willing to
去做任何詹特利先生准备并愿意让我去做的事
do whatever it is Mr Gently is ready and willing for me to do.
看来是醉的
Drunk, then.
-泰勒 -长官
-Taylor. -Sir.
去我家，把这个人擦洗干净，刮好胡子，给他穿上我的西装和衬衫，戴上领带
Go to my house. I want this man scrubbed, shaved and put in one of my suits, with a shirt and tie,
穿好鞋和袜子…我的袜子…然后再带回来
with shoes on, and socks...my socks...and brought back here.
詹特利先生，先生，我不能让其他男的靠近我…
Mr Gently, sir. I cannot let another man perform intimate...
如果我乐意…
And if I'm pleased...
擦洗，泰勒・・・从头到脚
Scoured, Taylor...head to toe.
-越快越好 -是，长官
-Quick as you can. -Yes, sir.
他名叫罗伯特・斯特拉顿
His name's Robert Stratton.
他是国家公园的看守人
He's a warden for the National Park.
他昨天晚上在码头上，观察鸟类迁徙
He was on the quay last night monitoring bird migration.
我只是复述，先生
I only know what I'm told, sir.
他是自己来的
He came in of his own accord.
他带着他女儿一起来的，那就是她。他妻子身体不好
He's here with his daughter, that's her, cos his wife's not well,
他女儿明显有些…
and his daughter's apparently a bit... WHISTLES
我们大概9点去了码头
We got to the quay around nine.
-对不起，夜里看鸟？ -对
-Yes... -Bird watching at night? Yeah.
我们不是整年都看，只是在迁徙开始的时候才看
Oh, we don't do it all year round, just when the migrations are on.
你不必非得看见它们，知道么
You don't have to see them, y'see...
能听见它们飞来了
you can hear 'em coming in.
有一个湖上出现了一对秋沙鸭，从丹麦飞来的
And we've had a couple of mergansers turn up on one of the lakes, from Denmark.
红色的秋沙鸭是很邋遢的鸟儿，在这些地方不常见
The red merganser's a scruffy bird, it's not very common in these parts.
它的脑袋很多毛，看起来乱糟糟的，总好像湿淋淋的…总是…总是…
It's got a tufty head, very untidy-looking, always bedraggled...always...always.
就是它
That's the one.
但是你昨天晚上没出去，只是坐在码头旁边的车里？
But you weren't out and about last night, you were sitting in your car on the quay?
我选了个角度可以看到海，我没看到有人来肯定是因为我正在看海
Angled, yeah, so I'm looking out to sea, which is what I must've been doing cos I didn't see anyone arrive.
可突然这个大块头从停小船的地方冒了出来
But suddenly this big chap turns up, down by the dinghy moorings.
他向我这个方向看了看，就转开了
He looks in my direction and turns away.
他来回走了一阵子，好像很不耐烦
And he walks up and down a bit, impatient, like.
后来我继续去观察天空，他走了
And then I'm checking the skies again and he's gone.
-后来怎么了？ -有些麻鹬和蛎鹬来了
-And what happened then? -Well, some curlew and oyster-catchers come over.
我们对鸟不是很感兴趣
We're not greatly interested in the birds.
哦，对不起……对
Oh, I'm sorry... No, um...
10点10分
Ten past ten,
又来了一个伙计
another chap turns up.
这个瘦一些，非常高…
A slighter man, quite tall...
恐怕我做不出更详细的描述，不过他坐在一根
I can't give much of a description, I'm afraid, but he's sitting on one of the
系船柱上，敲着大腿，好像在敲着一首歌的鼓点
bollards and he's tapping his thighs, you know, like he's drumming along to a song.
然后…就像我说过的，我决定今天晚上不干了，回家了
And... Well, as I say, I'd decided to call it a day and I drive off.
就是这个男的死了吗？
Was this the man who died?
等一下…
One minute...
我能去拿一下护照吗
Can I go and get the passports?
爱丽丝！爱丽丝！不，别动这个
Alice! Alice. No. Stop it.
对不起
I'm sorry.
给你，给你……
Here y'are, here y'are...
把你这个月看到的鸟列个单子
Make a list of every bird you've seen this month.
你能及时来真是太好了
It's very good of you to have come in so promptly.
你在码头上看到的就是这个人吗
Was this the man that you saw at the quay?
我的距离有点远
Look, I was some way away.
我不能肯定 嗯
I cannot swear to it. Right.
这两个人呢
What about these two?
他们在酒店
Yeah, they were at the hotel.
好的
Right.
我下山的时候进去喝了杯酒
I popped in for a drink on the way down.
他们就在酒吧里，很显眼  我回家的时候和这个人擦肩而过，他正在向码头方向走
They were at the bar, very smart. I passed this one as I was going home, he was coming down towards the quay.
他和什么人在一起吗？
Was he with anybody?
不，是一个人，拎着两个袋子
No, he was on his own, he was carrying two bags.
对不起，她……给你  爱丽丝，松手
Oh, I'm sorry, she's... Here y'are. Alice, leave it.
给你 接着写
There you go. Go on, carry on.
没事，没事
All right, all right...
我只想问你们几个问题，行吧
All I wanna do is ask you a few questions, that's all, right?
我只见过他两次，不过冈特就像是你认识了很多年的那种人
I only meet him twice, but Gunter, he is like someone you have known for years.
他很…
He is so...
你说话的时候他会看着你
He looks at you when you speak,
认真看着你
looks into you.
对你感兴趣
Is interested in you,
那样的笑容
and has such a smile.
我觉得…
I think...
SHE SPEAKS ITALIAN Ma non tutti, ovviamente.
Parla Italiano? No, veramente, no.
Mia moglie e nata a Napoli.
哦……他结婚了
Oh...he's married,
多可惜呀！
what a pity!
冈特曾经跟我说过一次意大利语
Gunter, he spoke Italian to me once,
虽然他过去的妻子是……丹麦人
though his wife was, um...  Danish.
-过去？ -他告诉我她今年死了
-WAS Danish? -She died this year, he say to me.
-我妻子也是 -我真抱歉
-So did mine. -I'm so sorry.
冈特昨天晚上走的时候…
When Gunter left last night...
-和哈迪曼一家一起走的 -是，还有别人走吗
With the Hardyments. Yes, did anyone else leave?
那些不喜欢德国人请喝啤酒的人
The ones that don't like a German buying the drinks
先是出去了，后来又从另一扇门进来了
and have walked out, they come back in through the other door.
我在酒吧里又忙了半个多小时，我一个人
I have been working the bar for half an hour or more, on my own.
喝酒免费，切克也回来帮忙了
And the drinks are free, but now Chick is back to help!
切克・谢弗斯什么时候回来的
And Chick Shavers came back when?
冈特和哈迪曼一走，切克就回来了
Gunter and the Hardyments go, and Chick is next to me straightaway.
-然后留在这里了 -对。
-And stays here? -Yes.
如果你想到
If you think
任何事要问我
of anything else you would like to ask me...
谢谢
Thank you.
给警察局打电话，他们可以放切克・谢弗斯走了
Call the station. They can let Chick Shavers go.
他有不在场证明
Got an alibi.
詹特利先生，先生
Mr Gently, sir.
我们干的怎么样？我还行吧
How have we done? Will I do?
你有梳子吗，警长
Have you got a comb, Sergeant?
给他
Give it to him.
你发现什么了
What did you find out?
里面有个人说向哈迪曼家打听一个叫茉莉的女人
Bloke in there says ask the Hardyments about a woman called Molly,
她在战争期间和他们住在一起
lived with them during the war.
和冈特有点关系
And then had a thing with Gunter,
后来自杀了
and then she later topped herself.
查尔纳！跟我走
China! Come with me.
不，你
No, you...
查尔纳，那是我的西装，别把烟头掉在上面
China, that's my suit. Don't put fag-ends in it.
-好的，詹特利先生 -如果我把你假扮成一位警官，你起码得装装样子
-Right, Mr Gently. -If I'm passing you off as a police officer, at least try and act like one.
我有个问题
I have a problem.
哈迪曼家的人记得开车超过了你，施麦克先生 只有你一个人
The Hardyments only remember driving past you, Mr Schmeikel. You alone,
没有施麦克夫人
not Mrs Schmeikel.
她是和我在一起
She was with me!
我在……我和他在一起
I was there... I was with him.
另一个证人只见到施麦克先生下山
Another witness only saw Mr Schmeikel walking down the hill.
他们撒谎
They are lying!
他们为什么撒谎
Why would they do that?
现在是谁在做调查
Who is the investigator here?
也许哈迪曼家想指责我，因为他们指责过我了
Perhaps the Hardyments wish to point the finger at me because they did it.
对不起，你是在指责哈迪曼家吗？
Um, I'm sorry, are you accusing the Hardyments?
对！为什么不
Yeah! Why not?
他们喝醉了，他们杀了他！
They get drunk and they kill him!
-威尔海姆，别  -因为什么原因杀他，施麦克先生
Wilhelm, nein. -Kill him for what reason, Mr Schmeikel?
因为他是德国人
For being German,
而且很成功，你们无法忍受因为我们比你们更坚定
and successful, a combination you cannot bear because we are more determined than you,
更勤奋，更有独创性，这让你们生气
more industrious, more ingenious, and this makes you angry.
哦，不可能，对不起，我忘了
Oh. Not possible. I'm sorry, I forgot.
你们英国人是这么开心
You British are so pleasant. SHE SPEAKS GERMAN
HE REPLIES IN GERMAN
随他们去
Leave 'em to it.
我替我丈夫道歉
I apologise for my husband.
他很生气
He is upset.
不过我很好奇，你觉得哈迪曼家是出于什么
I'm curious, though, as to what motive you think
动机把这件事归咎于你，如果他们认为是你杀了你父亲？
the Hardyments would attribute to you, if they thought you had killed your father.
-这个问题太扯了！ -威尔海姆
-Ridiculous question. -Wilhelm.
你们是不是认为我们现在是嫌疑犯
Are you considering us now suspects?
Britische Gerechtigkeit!
THEY SPEAK ANGRILY IN GERMAN
你都听到了？
Did you get all that?
她叫他别粗鲁…
She asked him not be rude...
然后他就爆粗了……他还告诉她
And then he was rude, and he told her to
从现在起别管了
leave it to him from now on.
他们吵了一架
They were having a row.
-我看是 -在那之前呢？
-I think. -And before that?
她说哈迪曼家为什么要在他给了他们那么大一个好处的时候杀了他？
She was saying why would the Hardyments kill Gunter when he was making them such a generous offer?
-什么好处？ -什么好处？-我怎么知道？
-What offer? -What offer? -How do I know?
他叫她闭嘴，再也别提这事
He told her to shut up and never mention it again.
干得好，查尔纳
Well done, China.
谢谢，詹特利先生
Thanks, Mr Gently.
-也许还会需要你 -对，
-May be needing you again. -Yeah.
"Niemals" 意思是“永不”
"Niemals", it means never.
查尔纳没能离开敦刻尔克海滩
China never got off the beach at Dunkirk.
他在德国战俘营里呆了5年
He spent five years in various Stalags.
DOGS BARK AND GEESE QUACK
把凳子拖出来
Pull up the crates.
你们也许觉得之前已经吃过这个了 不过，给你们上一课
Now, yer might think this is what yer had before...but there's a lesson in that.
拉长你们两次来访的时间
Put days between yer visits.
我不要 谢谢
None for me... Thank you very much.
好了 坐吧 坐吧
Oh, yeah, man. Tuck in, tuck in.
你们带来什么消息了吗？
Are yer back with news?
只有更多的问题
Just some questions.
好吧 我们喜欢来点儿智力测验 开始吧
Aye, well, we like a bit of a quiz. So fire away.
茉莉是谁？
Who's Molly?
谁跟你们说茉莉的？
Who talked to you about Molly?
为什么不跟我们说说她？
Why don't you just tell us about her?
吉米，坐下 吉米 吉米！
Jimmy. Sit down. Jimmy... Jimmy!
茉莉是吉米的妈妈
Molly was Jimmy's mum.
她是附近一个农场主的女儿
She was the daughter of a neighbouring farmer,
当她怀了私生子时――那是1940年1月
and when she got pregnant, out of wedlock, this is January 1940,
她父亲把她赶了出去 王八蛋
the father kicked her out. The bastard.
茉莉一直在学习当老师，挺有前途的，所以我和玛布丝收留了她
Molly was training to be a teacher, you know, something worthwhile, so Mabs and me, we took her in.
吉米出生后，玛布丝照料他，好让她完成学业
And when Jimmy was born, Mabs looked after him, so she could finish her training.
她后来成了个出色的老师，人家告诉我们
And she became a wonderful teacher, so we're told.
后来战争结束了，两年以后的47年5月2日，谁也没想到
Then the war ended and two year after, '47, 2nd of May, nay-body saw it coming.
她自杀了
She took her own life.
就在这个农场里
Here on the farm.
就是冈特住的那个阁楼
Up in the loft where Gunter stayed.
没有原因
No reason why.
没有遗言
No last note.
只有个空药瓶
Just an empty bottle of pills.
-冈特当时在哪里？ -被遣返了，两周前才回去
-Where was Gunter? Repatriated. -He'd gone back two weeks before.
她是怎么死的，死在哪里，又是为什么    大家都在谈，胡乱猜疑
Aye, the how she died, and the where and the why got everybody talking, you know, making assumptions.
茉莉和冈特之间发生了什么吗？
Did anything happen between Molly and Gunter?
能回答这个问题的两个人都死了，不过…
Well, now, the only two people who can answer that are dead, but...
我敢肯定他们之间肯定什么事也没有
I'm sure as damn-it certain nowt happened between 'em.
那么吉米呢？
What about Jimmy, then?
那时候他应该已经7岁了吧，茉莉死的时候？
He must have been about, I dunno, seven when Molly died.
也许他看到他们……看到他们在一起，也许他知道什么事儿
Maybe he saw 'em... You know, saw them together, maybe he knows something.
等冈特再回来的时候，对，大家又开始谈论了，说这和他有什么关系？
Look, when Gunter comes back again, aye, everybody's talking again, you know, was it to do with him?
可他在这里的时间不长，只是在农场看了一圈 我们都跟在他后面
But he hadn't been here long, looking round the farm. We're all traipsing after him.
一切都没变
Nothing has changed.
什么都没变
Nothing.
全和从前一样 一切！
All is as it was. Everything!
只有我们 我们变了！
Only us...we have changed!
看看你们大伙
Look at you all!
吉米
Jimmy...
你才这么大
You were that size!
还有你妈妈，茉莉
And your mother, Molly.
她现在在哪里
What is she now?
她是校长了？一定是个好老师
She's a head teacher? Must be such a fine teacher.
我也能见到她吗
Will I get to see her, too?
不能，嗯
No, um...
妈妈很久之前就不在了，冈特
We lost Mum a long time ago, Gunter.
那么多双眼睛盯着他看
'He had all these pairs of eyes staring at him,
寻找内疚的痕迹，哪怕是一丝的良心发现
'looking for a hint of guilt, a trace of bad conscience,
可我们看到的只有爱和悲伤
'and all we saw was love and sadness.'
和我们所有人的感觉一样
Same as what we all felt.
后来他在她自杀的那个阁楼里住了两个晚上
And yet, he spent two nights in the loft where she killed herself.
-可我们没告诉他她死在哪里 -我能看看吗
-Yeah, but we didn't tell him that's where it happened. -Mind if I have a look?
没什么可看的
There's not much to see, like.
到了
There you go.
像我说的，没什么可看的
Like I said, not much to see.
先生
Sir...
那是冈特的  一定是他落在这里的
That's Gunter's. He must've left it here.
-他去酒馆没带？ -应该没有 肯定是他放这儿了
-He didn't take it to the pub? -Can't have. He must've left it here.
-指纹 -指纹？你要指纹做什么？
-Fingerprints. -Fingerprints! What do you want fingerprints for?
冈特在这里的时候有没有说要给你们什么好处？
Did Gunter make you any kind of offer while he was here?
谁告诉你的？
Who told you that?
-有没有 -这个，我不是很明白他的意思
-Did he? -Well, I didn't really understand what he was on about.
说什么给免费给我们他公司的股票
Something to do with him giving us shares in his firm for free.
可我不喜欢股票的说法，所以拒绝了
But I didn't like the sound of shares, so I said no.
可他不断地提起，说要感谢我为他所做的一切
But he kept bringing it up, saying he wanted to thank me for what I did for him.
我对他说口头感谢就足够了
And I said to him words are enough.
你为他做了什么？
What did you do for him?
照我看没什么，可他说是我们中的一份子
Nowt, as far as I was concerned, but he said it was the community.
我们生活的方式
The way we lived.
你不像之前那么友好了
You're not looking as friendly as you were.
我需要农场所有人的指纹，谢谢
I'd like the fingerprints of everybody on the farm, please.
-你的车在哪里？ -还在警察局
-Where's your car? -Still at the station.
去取了你的车，把卡艾纳从酒吧救出来，给自己挣点加班费
Pick it up, scrape China off the bar and earn yourself some overtime.
把那个钱包清理干净，检查上面的指纹
I want that wallet dusted and cross-checked for fingerprints.
找出任何可疑之处，以及施麦克一家和他们的公司的一切
Find out anything and ever ything that you can about the Schmeikels and their company...
顺便说下这也是找卡艾纳的地方
That's where China comes in, by the way.
给德国大使馆打电话
Get on the phone to the German Embassy.
我想要了解下这个公司 从商业中可以了解一个人
I want a flavour of this company. The business will reflect the man.
谢谢你一直以来的照顾
Thanks. For the overtime.
话说回来 谁给我们引向茉莉的线索的
By the way, who gave us the heads up on Molly?
伯特高尔特 把眼珠子钓上来的那个渔夫
Bert Galton. The fisherman that hooked out the eyeball.
嗯
Yeah
奇科沙文思的朋友
Friend of Chick Shavers.
那现在还是吗
Is he now?
总督察
Chief Inspector.
想要点什么
What can I get you?
不用了 谢谢 我有公务在身
No. No, thank you, I'm on duty.
我想知道那晚你有没有注意到...
I wondered if you noticed the other night whether...
甘特斯科美克是不是从他钱包里拿钱来付酒钱的
Gunter Schmeikel paid for his drinks from a wallet?
钱包 是的
A wallet? Yes, he did.
伯特高特...他在吗
Bert Galton...is he here?
你知道 我下周末就离开了
You know, I leave at the end of next week.
（她说的意大利语）而且我好奇...
SHE SPEAKS ITALIAN And I was wondering...
你妻子给你做过意大利调味饭吗
Did your wife ever make you risotto di zucca?
做过 经常做
Yes, she did, often.
我说错话了
I have said the wrong thing.
没有 额...
No. No, er...
阿玛达 你是个很可爱的人 能认识你很高兴
Amata, you seem like a very lovely woman and it's been a pleasure to meet you.
但我现在得走了
But I have to go now.
祝你好运 詹特利先生
Good luck, Mr Gently.
哦 长官 尸检报告
Oh, sir, post mortem.
下面的脊柱因为压力而粉碎了 不是因为击打
The lower spine has splintered from pressure, not a blow.
对此他们还会做进一步检查 小伙子们还在取钱包上的指纹
They're gonna do more tests on that. The fingerprint boys are still working on the wallet. Too slow!
我已经训斥过他们了 长官 你听听这个
I have bollocked them, sir, but listen to this.
不来梅港市的德国警察正在调查威尔海姆斯科美克的欺诈事件...重大的欺诈案
German Police in Bremen are investigating Wilhelm Schmeikel for fraud...major fraud.
- 他干了啥 - 他从他父亲的公司非法转出一些资金到他的账户里
- What's he been up to? - Illegal transfer of funds from his father's company into his accounts.
为什么他要偷他父亲的钱呢
Why would he need to steal from his father?
因为甘特正打算将他的公司转为合作机构
Because Gunter was in the process of turning his company into a co-operative,
让每个员工都成为股票持有人
making every employee into a shareholder
- 这样威尔海姆就不是有效继承人了 - 把他带来
- and effectively...disinheriting Wilhelm! Pick him up!
打鼾声
< SNORING
头儿 紧急电话 港岸有纠纷
Guv, urgent call. Disturbance at the Mariners Rest.
- 狗屎 - 你才是狗屎  -还跟我犟啊
- Piece of shite! - Piece of shite yerself. - Spreadin' lies about my ma!
扁他 伙计
Clip him, man!
- 你给我少管闲事 - 他告诉你的 对吧
- Keep out of this, you! - He's the one telling yer, is he?!
- 你被记录在案了 你们俩都是 - 你这是在鼓动吧
- You're nicked, the pair of you! - Bit of a mover, aren't ya?!
拷上他 打电话求援
Cuff him, call for assistance.
走开 伙计们 让他们打完 笑声
Away, man, let them finish it! LAUGHTER
我听说你有点头绪了 总督察
I hear you've had a bit of a result, Chief Inspector.
我听说...小纳粹杀了老纳粹
I hear...the young Nazi killed the old Nazi.
很高兴未被监禁
Joy unconfined, eh!
闭嘴
Shut up.
费恶瑞先生
Mr Fairey.
- 是谁负责管辖这块的 - 不是我 长官
- Who's been doing all the talking round here? - Not me, sir.
那就让它立即停止 听到没 ... 你仍然在我的雷区内
Well, cut it out, d'you hear me! ..You are still on my radar.
他扔下他的妻子跑了 现正在去纽卡斯尔的公车上 试图弄条船
He ditched his wife and scarpered. He's on the bus to Newcastle. He's gonna try and get a boat!
- 我以为你拿了他的护照 - 双重国籍 头儿
- I thought you took his passport? - Dual nationality, sir.
- 他还有个丹麦护照 - 他母亲是丹麦人 阿玛达告诉我的
- He's got a Danish one an' all. - His mother was Danish. Amata told me.
我试过阻止他
I tried to stop him.
但你没打电话给我们 不是吗
Didn't telephone us, though, did you?
我告诉过他这样会使事情看上去更糟 这会把你牵进来
I told him this will only look bad, this will implicate you!
你英语很好 不是吗
Your English is excellent, isn't it?
好吧 这暂且搁一边 我们先澄清另一件事
Yes. Well, while we're at it, let's clear up one other thing.
你到底有没有和你丈夫一起去码头
Did you, or did you not, walk down to the quayside with your husband?
我本来是要去的
I was going to.
但是我感到不舒服 需要躺一会儿 所以...
But I was feeling ill. I needed to lie down for a while, so...
我待在了宾馆 他去了
I stayed here at the hotel and he went on ahead.
收拾下东西 下楼来
Collect your things and come downstairs, please.
慢慢来 喘息声
Take your time. OFFICER PANTS
也别慢的这么久
Not that long!
车站有人打电话说国家公园的守门人看到过甘特斯科美克
The station called to say a warden from the National Park claims to have seen Gunter Schmeikel.
- 斯卓登吗 昨天已经找过他了 - 不是的 长官
- Stratton? We talked to him yesterday. - No, sir.
是另一个守门人 说是今早在报上看到死者的照片的
Another warden, who saw the dead man's photo in the paper this morning
想起来两天前在哈德良长城附近的公园里看到过他
and remembers seeing him in the park near Hadrian's Wall two days ago.
他和一群人在一块儿 但是看到甘特斯科美克
He was with a group of people, but Gunter Schmeikel was seen
和斯卓登在讲话 然后一起离开了 长官
in conversation with Stratton, who then went off with him, sir.
在你之前到的那个男人就在不久前的一个晚上走了
The man who arrived just before you left the other night.
- 我们怀疑那人是甘特斯科美克 你说他是坐在一个船柱上的 是哪一个 - 那个
- The man we assumed was Gunter Schmeikel, you said he sat on a bollard. Which one? - That one there.
- 所以车子几乎是正对着他的 - 对
- So the car's pointing virtually straight at him? - Yes.
当你发动引擎是 车前灯亮了 他就正好在灯发出的光线中
And when you start your engine, the headlights come on and he's right in your beam?
- 应该是吧 对的 - 他大概在往上看
- I suppose so. Yes. - And presumably looks up.
- 可能吧 我不记得了 - 是还是不是
- If he did, I don't remember. - Well, did he or didn't he?
- 他就在你正前方 - 我当时正打算开车走人
- You were looking straight at him. - Well, I was driving off.
对 要离开你得倒车然后再向前走
Yes, and in order to leave, you have to go into reverse and then come forward again.
我倒车时是看着后面的
When I reverse, I look behind us.
你的一个看门的同事说
A colleague of yours, a fellow warden, says that
两天前看到你和甘特斯科美克一起在国家公园里
he saw you two days ago with Gunter Schmeikel at the National Park.
他说你和他讲话了 然后和他一起离开了
He says you spoke to him, then went off together on your own.
他说他是从报纸上的照片上认出死者的
He says he recognised the deceased from the newspaper photographs.
不可能 不可能是同一个人
No. No, can't be the same man.
嗯 可是确实是的 不是吗
Well, it was, though, wasn't it?
- 嗯 那天我见了很多人 - 很多德国人吗
- Well, I met a lot of people that day! - A lot of Germans?!
听着 该怎么讲呢 抱歉 我从没把这两者联系到一块
Listen, what can I say? I'm sorry. I never connected the two men.
现在你可以啦
Well, you can now.
- 那个坐在船柱上的人和跟你一起离开的是不是同一个人 - 别对他吼
- The man who sat on the bollard, was he the same man you went off with on the moors?! - Don't shout at him!
- 你为什么要吼 - 爱丽丝 别这样 求你了
- Why are you shouting? - Alice! Stop it, please.
没关系 没关系 爱丽丝 你是对的
It's all right, it's all right. Alice, you're quite right.
- 你是对的 我不应该吼的 - 你不该吼 一个叫詹特利的人是不该吼的
- You're quite right, I shouldn't. - You shouldn't. A man called Gently shouldn't shout!
你是对的 爱丽丝 抱歉 我道歉
No. You're right, Alice. I'm sorry. I apologise.
我爸爸有时也吼 不过只在屋子里
My dad sometimes shouts, only in the house.
从不在外面 你不能在外面吼 只能在屋子里吼
Never outside, you mustn't shout outside, only in the house.
- 你责怪我们吗 - 没有
- Do you blame us? - No.
我从没想到过...当然是同一个人了
It never occurred... Of course it was the same man.
太感谢上苍了 要不然我们又要找另一个德国人了
Well, thank God for that or we'd be looking for another German.
但是...你为什么要跟那个在公园里的人走呢
But...the man on the moors, why did you go off with him?
嗯 每个人到那儿的人都想要看看秋沙鸭
Well, everyone was hoping to see a Merganser.
吉姆 他本来是来见吉姆哈迪蒙特 但是吉姆这几天出去了
Jim, he was with Jim Hardyment, but Jim's got gout these days
他问我能不能带他到湖那边 然后我就答应了
and asks if I can take him down the lake, so I said sure, yeah.
我只是给他指了个正确的方向
I only point him in the right direction.
我可能还会再找你聊 斯特拉顿先生
I may need to speak to you again, Mr Stratton.
好的 当然 真对不起
Of course. Again, I'm sorry.
我的心思都在这里
Me mind's all over the place.
爱丽丝 你原谅我了吗
Alice. Am I forgiven?
追上了 追到了
Got yer. Got yer!
喇叭响
HORN BLARES
警察 对此我很抱歉
Police. Sorry about this...
喂 站住 站住  很好 好的
Hey, you stay where you are! You stay where you are! Right? Yeah.
怎么回事 额 你父亲发现你在偷他的钱
What happened, eh? Your father found out you were stealing from him?
- 啊 - 好的 来吧
- Agh! - Right, come on.
不好意思 只有我 局长有点忙
Sorry, it's just me. Chief Constable was busy.
好了 现在你可以走了 谢谢 听着...
All right, you can go now. Thank you. Listen...
不 不 不 去车里
No, no, no. In the car.
拜托 拜托听我讲 这对我来说很重要对你来说也一样重要 拜托你能听我讲
Please. Just, please listen. This could be as important for you as it is for me. Please listen.
- 现在你听我说 你不知道自己卷入了什么麻烦中吧 对吧 - 不 我当然知道 我知道
- No, you listen. You don't know how much trouble you're in? Right. - No, I know, I know.
我知道 在这儿你们会把人吊死
I know, you hang people here.
如果浪头扑向我 显然现在已经扑向了 那么没有人是会理解的
And if the tide is against me, which it is, then no-one is going to understand.
现在我父亲的公司是我的了
So my father's company, mine now,
我们可以以我们的方式来结算
we can pay our way!
- 我没听懂 - 哦 不 你懂得 你很聪明 并且...
- I'm not following you. - Oh, yes, you are. You are very smart, and...
并且我一直都有关注你
and I've been watching you.
你有关系在警局 我并没有试图想要逃避什么
You have connections. And I'm not trying to avoid anything.
只是 在德国 我们没有死刑
It is just that, in Germany, we do not have the death penalty.
所以我所请求的就是你能够帮助我引渡 能把我送还到不来梅港市
So all I ask is for you to work on my extradition, to have me sent back to Bremen.
如果你能帮我 我会给你20000英镑
For that, I will give you L20,000.
因为我没有杀害我的父亲 没有 我没有
Because I did not kill my father! Did not, did not!
听着...
Look...
为表示我的真心 只要一个电话...
To show good faith, with one phone call...
今天你的账号里就能多5000英镑
I put 拢5,000 into your bank account today.
现在 我唯一需要的就是你的卡号 好吗
Now. All I need is you give me your account number. Yes?
长官
Sir?
- 斯科美克有什么消息吗 - 额 还没有 长官
- Schmiekel, any news? - Er, no, sir.
- 验尸报告呢 - 也还没完成 长官
- Post-mortem tests? - No. Not yet, sir.
我刚刚被告知甘特斯科美克的钱包上检测到两个人的指纹
I've just been told there are two sets of prints on Gunter Schmeikel's wallet.
甘特和吉米哈德蒙特的
Gunter's and Jimmy Hardyment's.
吉米...你能告诉我
Jimmy... Could you tell me, please,
为什么甘特的钱包上有你的指纹吗
why your finger-prints were on Gunter's wallet?
我拿它看一下里面有没有我妈妈的照片
I took it to see if he had a photo of me mam in it.
什么时候的事
When was this?
昨晚在酒吧的时候
In the pub on the last night.
他唱着歌然后把外套扔给了我们
'He was singing this song and just threw his jacket to us.
他唱完时 我还拿着那个钱包
'But when he finished, I was still holding the wallet.'
还没来得及看里面
Hadn't looked in it yet.
防止有人看到...
In case anybody saw us...
因为我觉得自己像个小偷
Cos I felt like a thief.
所以我便把它收在身上
So then I kept it.
我把钱包放在阁楼的床头柜上 不过他似乎忘拿了
I put it in the bedside cupboard up in the loft as if he'd forgotten it.
那里面有你母亲的照片吗
And was there a photo of your mum in it?
吉米 你认为甘特需要对你母亲的死负责吗
Jimmy, do you think Gunter was responsible for your mother's death?
我知道威尔海姆和甘特的关系不好
I don't pretend that Wilhelm's relationship with Gunter was easy.
一直这样
It wasn't.
我想他们可能对一切事情的观点都不相同
I think, maybe, they disagree about everything,
但是有一位成功的父亲 儿子是很难做的
but to be the son of a successful father, it is hard.
然后这次旅行中 他被引荐给这些...
Then on this trip to be presented to these...
威尔海姆称他们为农夫...他们的确是
Wilhelm calls them peasants... and they are.
从最好的层面来说 他们是农夫
In the best sense, they are.
但是后来他父亲说 我们也应该成为这样的人
But then his father is saying, these people are what we must be like.
我们的公司应该成为这样 我们应该这样互相照顾
This is what our company must be like, this is how we must look after one another,
真的 这不关商业
and really, this is not business!
你在哪里见到哈德蒙特的
And you met the Hardyments where?
威尔海姆的父亲研究鸟类 哈德蒙特带我们去荒地的
Wilhelm's father studies birds and the Hardyments took us to the moors.
跟我讲讲这件事
Tell me about that.
没什么好讲的
There's nothing to tell.
我们不喜欢哈德蒙特 我肯定哈德蒙特也不喜欢我们
We don't like the Hardyments and I'm sure the Hardyments don't like us.
但是甘特很开心
But Gunter is happy.
非常开心
So happy.
嗯 有人想要抢他的照相机
Well, someone tried to snatch his camera.
没得逞 但威尔海姆十分生气
They didn't get it, but Wilhelm was very angry.
他想找出这个人 因为事情发生在甘特离开河边时
He wanted to find this person, because it happened while Gunter was off at the lake.
但是甘特说 算了 算了 然后我们就没追究
But then Gunter was saying, leave it, leave it, so we leave it.
拜托了 我必须得重申 因为我知道
Please, I have to keep saying this, because I know it is true.
威尔海姆绝不可能杀害他的父亲 绝对不会 这点我确定
Wilhelm could never have killed his father, never. This I know.
你丈夫因从他父亲那里偷钱构成欺诈罪而被调查 弗 斯科美克
Your husband is being investigated for fraud, Frau Schmeikel, for stealing from his father.
可能是他预料到他父亲不会给他继承权 你知道这件事吗
Perhaps in anticipation of his father disinheriting him. Did you know that?
他从没跟你讲过 对吗
He never told you, did he?
好好想想吧
Do some thinking, please.
- 詹特利先生 - 卡艾纳
- Mr Gently. - China.
有人让我接了一个来自不来梅港市的电话 是那儿的警察打来的
I was asked to take a call from Bremen, from the police there.
他们不会说英文 但是你得知道这个 半小时前
They couldn't speak English, but wanted you to know that, half an hour ago,
威尔海姆斯科美克从他的银行账户里
Wilhelm Schmeikel instructed his bank
转了5000英镑到约翰巴克斯警长的账户里
to transfer five grand into the account of Sergeant John Bacchus.
他们想知道是否应该转这笔账
And they want to know whether they should let the transfer go ahead?
- 巴克斯在哪儿 - 他刚进来 长官
-Where is Sergeant Bacchus? - He's just come in, sir.
拷着那个德国人
With the German in handcuffs.
- 他看上去很开心 - 头儿...
- Looking very happy with himself. - Guv...
威尔海姆斯科美克想要录口供 我会为你安排好的
Wilhelm Schmeikel wishes to make a statement. I'll get him lined up for you.
现在还不是时候 警长
Not yet, Sergeant.
可以 让他们转
Yes. Tell them to go ahead with it.
跟我走
With me, please.
我 额...
I, er...
在罗伯特斯特拉顿这人身上需要点你的意见
I want your opinion on Robert Stratton.
可现在在这儿了 现在我们把这带来了
They're here now, we've got 'em now!
我跟你讲让它随着时间溃烂得了
I'm talking about you letting it fester for years, man!
在这个时候我觉得这样做最好 詹特利先生
I thought it was the best thing to do at the time! Mr Gently.
看我们刚刚挖到了什么
Look what we just dug up!
- 我们需要尽快给威尔海姆录口供 - 你跟着我
- We must talk to Wilhelm as quickly as possible. - You stick with me.
是我发现莫莉的 你知道的
I was the one who found Molly, y'see,
她躺在床上 拿着这个盒子
and there she was, on the bed, holding this box.
- 当我看到这些时... - 你本该看看内容或是告诉别人这件事
- And when I saw them... - You should've read them or told somebody about 'em!
那样做不对 这些东西太隐私了
It wouldn't have been right. They were too personal!
她又没有把它们藏起来 不是吗
She wasn't hiding them, was she?!
我不想有人做些愚蠢的事 比如说去找那个让她做出这样的事的人
I didn't want anyone doing anything stupid like going after whoever had made her do such a thing. that's why I do that
我把它们拿出来到她以前常坐的地方 然后我看了这些东西...后来把他们埋在了树下
I took 'em outside to where she used to sit and read and...buried 'em under a tree.
你在胡说些什么
Now what yer blabbing for?
因为他觉得甘特的事是我们的吉米干的 对吗
Cos he thinks our Jimmy did for Gunter, don't yer?!
如果是吉米干的 那我们不都参与其中了 他跟我们在一起的
Well, if our Jimmy done it, we're all in it, aren't we? He was with us!
这些都有将近20年了 我是说 这些能证明些什么呢
These must be nearly 20 years old! I mean, what are they gonna prove?!
我们看看能证明什么 好吗
Let's find out, shall we?
我不要打开它们 我不想知道这些信是哪里来的
I'm not opening 'em! I don't wanna know who they're from.
我可以吗
May I?
当你带甘特去荒地时
When you took Gunter out onto the moors,
我想你见到过罗伯特斯特拉顿 其中的一个看门人
I gather you met Robert Stratton, one of the wardens.
鲍勃斯特拉顿 是见到过
Bob Stratton, aye.
甘特正跟我们讲他被击倒的那个晚上 然后鲍勃便加入了
Gunter was telling us about the night he got shot down, and Bob joined with.
- 甘特后来跟他一起走了 - 嗯 我让他带甘特去湖边的
- And Gunter went off with him? - Well, I asked him to show him down to the lake.
你认识罗伯特斯特拉顿多长时间了
How long have you known Robert Stratton?
他是战后刚来这儿的
Came here just after the war.
他来自桑德兰 （英国英格兰东北部港市） 他的生活可真悲惨 妻子精神一直不好 还有那可怜的姑娘 他的...
A Sunderland man. What a life he has, wife on the verge all the time and that poor lassie of his...
他做了该做的一切 他是个好家伙
He does everything. He's a sound bloke.
它们全被审查过 我是说 这上面线索寥寥无几
They're all censored. I mean, there's a few clues and that.
如果看到电话亭 你介意停一下吗 我得打个电话 很快的
If we see a phone-box, d'you mind if I stop and make a quick call?
- 有什么急事吗 - 没什么急事
- Something urgent? - No.
- 你好 - 你好
- Hello. - Hello.
- 我们可以... - 进去吧 进去吧 进去吧
- Can we...? Come in, come in! Come in.
敲门声 有人吗 哦 哦 抱歉 抱歉
HE KNOCKS ON DOOR Hello? Oh! Oh, sorry. Sorry.
水溅声 能给我们点时间吗
WATER SPLASHES > Can you give us a minute, please?
这是我妈妈 她就在里面
It's me mam, she's in the altogether.
- 我妈妈 她在里面 你看 - 我们会等会的
- Me mam, she's in the altogether. Look. - Yeah, we'll wait.
爱丽丝 进来 进来吧
Alice, come on. Pack it in! Come on.
额 抱歉 我妻子现在不能自己洗澡或穿衣服
Er, sorry, me wife can't wash or dress herself at the moment.
斯特拉顿先生
Mr Stratton.
我本打算去找你的
Yeah, I was gonna come and see you.
因为我意识到我之前也见过旅馆的那对年轻的德国夫妇
Cos I realised that I must have also seen that young German couple from the hotel before.
在荒地时 和哈德蒙特家一起的 我是说那时我没跟他们讲过话 但是 额...
On the moors, part of the Hardyment group. I mean, I never spoke to them at the time, but, er...
我猜他们也没认出我来 因为如果认出的话他们可能在旅馆时会说点什么的
I guess they didn't recognise me either cos they would've said something at the hotel, perhaps.
那年轻的夫人说当甘特斯科美克跟你走了然后回来时
It's just that the young wife says that when Gunter Schmeikel came back from going off with you,
抱怨有人想抢他的照相机
he complained that someone tried to snatch his camera.
什么 她说是...我没偷...
What? She said it was... I didn't steal...
我干嘛要偷他的照相机 你听着
Why would I steal his camera? Now listen, no.
不 他是个 他是个怪人
No, he was a, he was a strange one, that one.
我并没有讲她指责是你干的 斯特拉顿先生 但请继续说
I didn't say that she'd accused you, Mr Stratton. But please go on.
甘特斯科美克哪里奇怪了
Gunter Schmeikel was strange in what way?
你知道的 他很奇怪...
Well, you know, he was odd...
开始时很友好 但是当我们到达河边时
Nice enough to start off with, but when we got down to the lake,
他转向我们 说"继续 继续"
he turns on us, "Go. Go on. Go on!"
并开始说我在监视他
and starts saying I was spying on him.
嗯 然后我就走开了 让他自己发疯去
Well, you know, I just walk away. I leave him to it.
这个人在前一天下午行为那么古怪
And yet, this was the man who was behaving so strangely earlier in the afternoon,
但在码头时你却没认出他
that you failed to recognise him at the quayside?
是的 对此我已经做出过解释了
Yeah, well, I've already explained that!
码头的人没让我联想到那个人 一次也没有
The man at the quayside didn't bring to mind that man, not once.
意大利 44
Italy '44...
达拉谟步兵团
Durham Light Infantry?
是的
Aye.
你呢
You?
米德尔塞克斯团 然后...
Middlesex Regiment, then...
..加入了柴郡团
..joined up with the Cheshire.
应该对你们有点打击
Took a bit of a hammering.
-是的 - 大部分时间我们部队都很平静
- They did. - We had a quiet time for the most part.
- 抱歉 我觉得你的妻子... - 不
- Sorry, I think your wife's... - No.
别 别 不 进来 进来
Come on. Come on. No. In. In. Come on.
爱丽丝 不要这样 别这样做 爱丽丝
Alice, don't. Don't do that, Alice.
爱丽丝 离火远点
Don't! Alice, come away from the fire.
离火远点 这才是个乖姑娘
Away from the fire. There's a good girl.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thanks.
你工作时怎么办
What happens when you're working?
他们待在房间里
They stay in their rooms.
那是...
Does that...?
他把她们锁起来吗
Does he lock 'em in?
斯特拉顿是嫌疑人吗
Is Stratton a suspect?
当然是的 怎么这么问
Yeah, of course he is. Why?
那这会帮助你还是会阻碍你
Would that help or hinder you?
- 不明白你的问题 - 那对你是有利还是有弊
- Don't understand the question. Would that be good or bad for you?
对我
For me?!
我糊涂了 头儿
I don't get you, guv.
不来梅港的警察打电话来了
The police in Bremen rang.
威尔海姆斯科美克往你账户里转了5000英镑
Wilhelm Schmeikel's transferring L5,000 into your account.
- 我想告诉你的 - 嗯 你有两个小时的时间告诉我
- I was gonna tell ya. - Well, you've had two hours.
我在等钱到位
I was waiting for the money to be in place.
那会改变他的想法
It could've changed his mind!
继续撒谎 警长
Try again, Sergeant.
听着...
Look...
好吧 我想向你证明我能以我的方式办好事情
OK, I wanted to prove to you that I could get things done, my way!
头儿 拜托 听我说
Look, guv. Guv, listen, please.
你想想 这家伙没想承认罪行 不是吗
Think about it! The guy wasn't just gonna go and confess, was he?
那这就是证据
This is proof!
- 这5000英镑会让他得到什么 - 20000 - 20000
- What was he gonna get for his 5,000? - 20,000. - 20?!
现在只有五千 只要我把他送遣回国就能拿到剩下的钱
Five now and the rest when I got him extradited to Germany.
你不能这么做
You can't do that!
我知道 但是他不知道 不是吗
Well, I know that! But he doesn't know that, does he?
他绝望了 绝望了 因为他有罪
He's desperate. He's desperate, because he's guilty.
那吉米哈德蒙特以及哈德蒙特一家呢
What about Jimmy Hardyment and the Hardyment family?
吉米的指纹遍布钱包
Jimmy's fingerprints are all over the wallet.
你对罗伯特斯特拉顿的记忆间断就没有怀疑吗
Are you not bothered about Robert Stratton's memory lapses?
长官 威尔海姆斯科美克杀了他父亲
Sir, Wilhelm Schmeikel killed his father,
为了躲避这个 他试图买票回家
and in an attempt to avoid the news, tried to buy his way home!
谢谢 对 很好
Thank you. Right. Very good.
是的 我们现在需要把这5000英镑转回到...
Yes, we now need to transfer the 5,000 back to the...
什么
What?
多少钱
By how much?
我一会儿回给你好吗
Can I call you back, please?
谢谢
Thank you.
你账户的钱不够退还5000英镑 只能退还
Your bank can't repay the full L5,000. They can only manage...
4782英镑
L4,782.
我的透支额
My overdraft.
你所超支的金额最终被填补了
Which you exceeded and has consequently been cancelled,
也就说 目前你受贿了
meaning, as of now, you just took a bribe.
不 长官...你知道事实不是这样的
No, sir... You know that's not true!
让我告诉你我知道什么吧
No, let me tell you what I know.
你决定走捷径让威尔海姆的罪名成立
You decided to cut corners to incriminate Wilhelm Schmeikel,
而你最后做到的是让自己变得有罪
and what you've really managed to do is incriminate yourself.
找出这些信是谁写的
Find out who the man is in those letters.
他的名字被黑掉了
His name is blacked out.
他笑了笑
HE SCOFFS
这个任务很简单 警长
It's a simple task, Sergeant.
- 这信上记录了很多详细的东西 - 这事谁都能干
- There's lots of circumstantial stuff in them. - Anyone can do that.
是的 那快去做啊
Yeah, so go and do it.
- 这是对我的惩罚 是吗 - 我不在乎你怎么看待的
- My punishment, is it? - I don't care how you look at it.
Just do as I tell you for once!!
What are you gonna do while I'm stuck in some office
30 miles away for the rest of the night?
I'll talk to some senior officers who might just be able to save you
from a dishonourable discharge from the police service!
Hello.
Speaking.
Tomorrow?
Just hold on a minute.
Yes, that will be fine.
Good work.
Good work, Detective Sergeant Bacchus.
Exc..
Excuse me!
Hello?!
There's no need to shout in here.
Can I move on to the Ss, please. Aye.
Thank you. S for Stratton.
Yes, I can feel myself inhabiting the role of the detective.
Accumulating information,
examining motives and evidence, you know.
But I tell yer how I decide who's done it,
cos it might be useful to you as a technique, y'know?
Out of the mouths of babes in China...
What I do is this -
I ask myself,
who would you not want to be right now, China?
What's it like speaking German after all these years?
It's not the speaking of it...
It's hearing it again.
So...
Are you not going to ask me who I think done it?!
Nope. I think you should get some sleep, China.
German Police and Embassy officials first thing in the morning.
Right, Mr Gently.
Robert Stratton.
Robert Stratton...
"By the King's order the name of Corporal Robert C Stratton,
"Durham Light Infantry,
"was published in the London Gazette on the 4th of August 1944,
"as mentioned in a dispatch for distinguished service.
"I am charged to record His Majesty's high appreciation."
Signed Secretary of State for War.
Mentioned in a dispatch for what?
Bloody hell! He killed three men with his own hands.
Ich flehe Sie an, bitte...
KNOCK ON DOOR
Ich moechte an die deutsche Justiz ausgeliefert werden.
Full post-mortem report, and DS Bacchus is on the phone for you.
Thank you. Taylor? Sir.
I sent someone to fetch Mr Stratton in. Is he here yet?
I'll go and check for you, sir.
Sir, I've got the identity of the man in the letters. Molly's man.
Right, he was based up here with the Royal Signals from '45
till he was posted to Palestine, where he died of diphtheria.
Now this was two weeks before Molly Hardyment killed herself.
And he was married, which may have some bearing.
Although, of course, none of this actually solves anything,
since the important thing is that people thought
it might have been down to Gunter.
D'you wanna say something, guv?
Well done. Well done.
Right. Am I still on the case?
You were never off it, or didn't you notice?
Sometimes we have to take the long way round, Sergeant.
Yeah, it's amazing what a bit of donkey work can do, innit?
Now, listen, I came up with one more thing. It's the...
Yeah, tell me when you see me.
Well? Doesn't look good, Mr Gently.
He's begging to be extradited... and admitting everything.
He admitted killing his father?
Well, he said he'd say he did it if they sent him back to Germany.
But then he said he didn't do it.
One thing's for certain, Mr Gently.
He don't want to hang.
Do you think he did it? Yes.
Well, no.
Well, maybe.
The Germans think he did it, sir.
Hm.
I ask you, Chief Inspector, if I wanted to kill him,
why wouldn't I have done it out at sea?
Claim it as an accident?!
You can't sail.
And your wife was with you.
I did not kill my father!
And I'd be inclined to believe you, because,
to do this,
to inflict this amount of pain...
and I am assured he would have been in extreme agony... Well...
There are simpler and less suspicious ways
to dispatch a father.
However, in your latest statement,
you still insist that you walked down to the quayside with your wife.
The truth, Mr Schmeikel, might just save your life.
However, if you persist...
It was too suspicious to say that I was there on my own.
I am being investigated for stealing from my father.
Oh.
Good. Better...
So, who saw you on your own?
The Hardyments.
They were the first to pass you, yeah?
The first, no.
The only ones. There were no others.
Mr Schmeikel, you were seen and passed by two cars.
No, by the Hardyments only.
There were no other cars!
You're telling me, no other cars?!
Parked cars, yes.
One on the street and one on the harbour.
The harbour one. What make?
A small family car.
Blue, I think.
Where's Stratton? What room's he in?!
Oh, he's still not here, sir.
Mr Stratton.
Hello!
Mr Stratton!
Anybody!
BANGING
You all right, son? Yes, sir.
Where's the wife and daughter?
Upstairs, I think, but he went out maybe five, ten minutes ago.
What're yer doing?
Why are yer pulling us?!
Just taking a short cut. Wanna get to the top.
I don't want to. I don't like it.
TYRES SCREECH
No!
Come on, Alice.
Come on.
When was...
the best time up here?
When was that, do you reckon?
When it was frosty.
It was cold and frosty.
It was a cold and frosty morning!
I remember. The mist was down there, wasn't it?
Was...was like,
like we were in heaven!
Like, like me and you were angels.
Dad!
Let her go!
Stratton!
There's a good girl.
Come on.
Sir? What?
Call the station.
Tell them to release Jimmy Hardyment and Schmeikel.
And call an ambulance for Mrs Stratton.
Non-urgent.
Sergeant.
Whatever part you played, thank you.
Much appreciated, as you know.
Let's get this straight. I did nothing to help you.
The money's going back into your bank account.
Personally, I think you should be done for attempting to bribe a police officer.
You know, Sergeant, you are really quite an unpleasant chap.
Why don't you piss off back to where you came from?
Auf Wiedersehen, Herr Sergeant.
Trudi.
Sorry.
You joining us?
It's fate, isn't it?
I could've been anywhere on the moors that day.
And if Jim Hardyment hadn't've been there, I'd never have gone over.
But over I went,
and there's this smart German bloke,
laughing about being a bomber pilot,
and how he was shot down over the Tyne 20 years ago.
Laughing about it. Aye, man.
What?
1944, I'm out in Italy.
Yeah you were mentioned in dispatches, weren't you? Aye.
For killing three guards.
They were the enemy.
We'd been captured.
How did yer kill 'em?
I have admitted killing Gunter Schmeikel.
You broke their necks, didn't yer! There you are, there!!
We were unarmed. We did what we had to do.
And this time?
Well, I was trying to tell you.
Out in Italy, after we'd escaped,
I get a letter telling us me wife and bairn have been killed
in an air-raid in Sunderland.
We lived in Sunderland.
So you kill an innocent man 20 years later! Innocent? Well...
Who's innocent in this world?
Except me daughter.
But I'll tell you, I'd never have thought
I'd feel the way I did when I heard that Gerry laughing.
I'm not saying that I never thought about me first family,
cos what with me second wife and Alice,
you know, who wouldn't wonder what might have been?
But...
That laughter, though.
And Jim was joining in as well.
Fair dos, cos I'd never told anyone.
So...
When you go off with Gunter Schmeikel on the moors...
Oh, I'm gonna confront him. And I do.
But before I mean to, cos suddenly...
This is the new Canon.
You know about cameras?
It's the world's first.
You think I want to look at your bloody camera?
What do you do?! You think you can carry on like nothing's happened.
Like, standing around laughing and smiling.
Well, not in front of me, mate.
Just go away.
Not in front of me!
Don't think he knew what was happening,
cos I'm like,
you know, tongue-tied. I can't get me words out.
And...
Well, I'm embarrassed.
And I wander off.
Yesterday evening, when I knew I wasn't gonna get away with this,
I thought about telling yer that I went to see him the following night
to apologise and it got out of hand,
how I didn't mean to kill him, y'know, go for manslaughter.
But that still left us with the same problem.
Me wife and Alice, cos with me in prison,
them two's put away in mental homes and...
So...
Better to kill them?
Better if you'd've let us kill Alice, aye.
You frequent loony bins, do yer?
No, you know all about them though, yeah?
Well, try putting your own children in them!
If she were dead, I'd be joining her.
As it is, she's left here, cared for by who? You?!!
You?
And I keep feeling this...
Me, the quiet man,
the patient man everyone admires.
But from when I got home after that tussle...
..I got angry.
I can't tell yer. I can't sleep for this rage.
Have I got to do everything by me bloody self?
Can you not see that the bloody fire's gone out?!
I can't stop hearing him laughing, like he's laughing at me life.
Some wood on the fire!
And I knew I was gonna kill him.
And end it?
How did the opportunity arise?
Well, like everything in life, you need the luck.
I figured rich folk like that would be staying at the hotel
so I went there first.
Yes. We will be spending the last night on the boat.
My father's already having drinks...
There's his son settling his bill and telling the receptionist everything I needed to know.
Where his dad was, what time they were meeting him.
We will go and meet my father soon.
So I drive down to the Mariners, go in...
RAUCOUS SINGING
And there's laughing boy up and singing Geordie songs to everyone!
So that helps fuel us.
But there's too many folk around, so I take meself off to the quay,
cos I know he's meeting his son there.
And I wait.
Why did you admit to being the fella in the car?
Well, I didn't know who'd seen us.
Could've been the Hardyments, in which case, why hadn't I,
y'know, owned up?
By this time I was still hoping to get away with it.
So you stitch up the son?
Can we stick to the order of events?
You're back on the quayside.
I take it Shavers came and went?
Thank God.
And then?
Well, just in case this Gunter came,
I parked in the shadows and waited and hoped.
I gave meself a time frame of 10.14.
If he hasn't turned up, I'm out of there.
At nine minutes past...
GUNTER SINGS
?Saved coos an' calves
?O' the famous Lambton worm. ?
And then I heard someone coming.
But I'm happy to wait for him to go now, cos I knew.
When your Gunter went in the water,
he went in alive.
Why was that so important?
Why not just snap his neck and kill him?
Cos when my wife and bairn died in that raid,
they weren't killed by a direct hit.
They were in the cellar
and a water-main burst.
But they couldn't get 'em out cos of the fallen masonry.
So they drowned.
Let's all have a laugh, eh?
Ah, good, you're still here. Come with me.
Guv?
I found out about Stratton's war record last night.
I knew when we spoke on the phone...
But if I'd told you last night,
his wife would still be alive now, wouldn't she?
For better or for worse.
Come on!
I want to show you something.
Stay!
Stay.
That's right, you tell 'em. You show them who's the boss. Come on!
Now make a fuss of 'em.
Good doggies.
Right, we'll be heading back, Mr Gently.
I'm gonna look after the chickens and the ducks,
and the geese.
And the doggies.
Thank you.
That's what we're here for.
Come on then. Eh!
Right, now we have to repay that bribe you took.
Sir, it wasn't a bribe.
I ran up an overdraft limit.
Right, well let's clear it. Here. Have this.
Go on.
Oh, no. No, I'm not taking that.
Yes, you are. You can repay me 拢10 a month. No.
拢10 a month without fail.
I don't want it, sir. Have it.
There's enough in there, so you can keep the MG as well.
Can't have you driving around in something sensible.
Tomorrow, first thing.
(WHISTLES) In you go.
Thank you, sir.
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd
E-mail subtitling@bbc.co.uk